<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Nathans parable. Sins discovery, with it's [sic] filthy secret lurking in the brest of men. Or, some few discoveries what the sinfulness of sin is, and spoile it hath made on man, in nine particulars. With the sad experience of it on the author: written, if it may be, to warn all men, especially, the saints, to take heed and to beware of sin. With a letter written to his excellency the Lord General Cromwell. By Edmund Chillenden.</title>
            <author>Chillenden, Edmund, fl. 1656.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79511</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3877</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E723_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207232</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866298</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866298</idno>
            <idno type="VID">166768</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79511)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 166768)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 111:E723[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Nathans parable. Sins discovery, with it's [sic] filthy secret lurking in the brest of men. Or, some few discoveries what the sinfulness of sin is, and spoile it hath made on man, in nine particulars. With the sad experience of it on the author: written, if it may be, to warn all men, especially, the saints, to take heed and to beware of sin. With a letter written to his excellency the Lord General Cromwell. By Edmund Chillenden.</title>
                  <author>Chillenden, Edmund, fl. 1656.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 16 [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sin --  Meditations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:166768:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Nathans Parable. SINS DISCOVERY, With it's Filthy Secret Lurking in the breſt of Men.</p>
            <p>OR, Some few Diſcoveries what the ſinfulneſs of Sin is, and ſpoile it hath made on man, in nine particulars.</p>
            <p>With The Sad experience of it on the Author: written, if it may be, to warn all men, eſpecially, the Saints, to take heed and to beware of Sin.</p>
            <p>WITH A Letter written to his Excellency the Lord General CROMWELL.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Edmund Chillenden.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Lam. 3.1.</hi>
                  </bibl> I am the man that <hi>(have ſinned, and for that)</hi> have ſeen affliction by the rod of his wrath.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Heb. 4.12, 13.</hi>
                  </bibl> Take heed brethren leſt there be in any of you an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil heart of unbelief in departing from the living God, leſt any of you be hardned through the deceitfulneſs of Sin.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London,</hi> 1653</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:166768:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:166768:2"/>
            <head>To all the Congregations of Saints walking in the faith and Order of the Goſpel in England, Ireland and Scotland.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Precious hearts,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have a ſad theam to preſent you with, it is of <hi>ſin,</hi> and the ſad effects it hath produced in the world, eſpecially on man, and in particular on my ſelf, ſo that I may ſay in the words of the Prophet, <hi>Lam. 5.16. The Crown is faln from my head, wo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me that I have ſinned:</hi> for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>miſchief</hi> hath attended me; yea <hi>deſtruction</hi> and <hi>ruine</hi> in all things that can be thought of here below: and were it not but that <hi>God</hi> who I have ſo offended had appeared to me indeed, as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Eph. 2.4 Rich in mercy and in great love,</hi> infinite and beyond all expreſſion, I had for ever periſhed, and been <hi>puniſhed with ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting deſtruction from the preſence of the Lord and the glory of his power,</hi> Theſſ. <hi>1.5.</hi> for I deſerved no leſs, ſo that truly I have experienced that good ſaying of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> That where <hi>ſin hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded, grace hath much more</hi> (yea exceeding much more) <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded,</hi> Rom. <hi>5.20.</hi> Oh rich grace, rich grace, and great mercies, and loving kindneſs, they are paſt finding out, they cannot be fathom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they are <hi>high,</hi> they are <hi>deep,</hi> they are <hi>long,</hi> and they are <hi>broad,</hi> ſo that I cannot but ſtand and admire, what <hi>manner of love it is that he hath beſtowed on me, 1</hi> Joh. <hi>2.1.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have therefore ſent to you theſe few lines, that you may take heed and beware of <hi>ſin,</hi> for it is a moſt <hi>deceitful,</hi> yea a moſt <hi>deadly</hi> cruel <hi>enemy,</hi> for it maketh ſuch ſpoile on a man where it gets footing, that if <hi>mercy,</hi> yea <hi>rich mercy</hi> and <hi>love</hi> from God <hi>do</hi> not ſtep in to help, it deſtroyeth <hi>ſoul</hi> and <hi>body,</hi> good name, relations, and all that is neer and dear: therefore take heed and beware of <hi>ſin,</hi> and take that good counſel of the Apoſtle, <hi>1 Cor. 16.13. Watch ye, ſtand faſt in the faith, quit you like men, be ſtrong in the Lord, and in the power of his might,</hi> Eph. <hi>6.10.</hi> for if you do not, ſin will break in upon you, and make grievous ſpoile and havocke.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:166768:3"/>
            <p>For want of keeping this guard, it hath broken in on me, like an inundation of water, and yet I thought once my <hi>mountain</hi> was ſo ſet, and ſo <hi>ſtrongly founded,</hi> that it was not poſſible it could be <hi>moved, Pſal. 30.7.</hi> when I was in my <hi>Tranquility, and the candle of the Lord ſhone upon my head, I ſaid I would dye in my neſt, and multiply dayes as the ſand, I would ſpread my root by the waters, I ſhould flouriſh,</hi> Job <hi>29.3, 18, 19, 20.</hi> all went well, I had attained to ſome good progreſs in the knowledge of <hi>God,</hi> and the practice of the things of <hi>God,</hi> and I was now ſafe, and my heart ſpoke a great deal of peace, but behold when I thus ſlept, the <hi>ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my ſin</hi> came and ſtole in upon me, and I will tell you how.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> Firſt I grew a little cold and careleſs in the matters of <hi>God,</hi> in thoſe cold, mad, and diſtempered yeers <hi>1647. and 1648.</hi> and then ſin took occaſion, and by my baſe heart deceived me, preſently runs and layeth hold on me, <hi>tempteth</hi> me, and <hi>draweth me away,</hi> Jon. <hi>1.14, 15,</hi> compare <hi>Rom. 7.11.</hi> and ſo hath <hi>ſlaine, wounded,</hi> and <hi>deſtroyed</hi> me.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> After that I was thus <hi>inticed,</hi> my <hi>heart</hi> being by <hi>ſin deceived,</hi> then I became it's <hi>ſlave</hi> to ſerve it; and this will be the caſe of every one that ſin layeth hold of. Now I muſt provide to lay alwayes for the carrying of it cloſe and ſecret; and here cometh <hi>vows, oaths, wiſhes, execrations,</hi> and all to ſave, cover, and hide this ugly <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Then <hi>ſin</hi> will ſeem very <hi>fair,</hi> and <hi>ſmile</hi> on you, <hi>flatter</hi> your <hi>heart,</hi> and if he cometh once to be touched, to be diſcovered, and feareth he ſhall be diſlodged, he now will come with the help of his firſt-born the divel, and belay you on every ſide. Firſt, on the <hi>right hand,</hi> and on the <hi>left,</hi> under <hi>pretence</hi> of <hi>good</hi> towards <hi>God,</hi> towards his <hi>wayes,</hi> to thy <hi>ſelf</hi> and <hi>relations.</hi> For ſo have I found it, that when I had ſome yeers ſince abandoned all the thoughts of any ſuch thing; and in <hi>July 1650.</hi> had earneſtly beſought the <hi>Lord</hi> for his <hi>favour and peace</hi> for my former evils, and that he would now <hi>pardon</hi> and paſs by my ſin, and <hi>hide his face from my ſin;</hi> the which he did, and ſpoke much peace to me, and did deliver my ſoul from the jaws of deſtruction; when death had ſurrounded me, I then did vow to the Lord to honour him and ſerve him all my dayes, but there was more ſnares beſet me. For when in the yeer <hi>1652.</hi> I was charged with evil by Maſter <hi>Thomas Halhead</hi> and his wife, now
<pb facs="tcp:166768:3"/> behold how <hi>ſin</hi> beſet me, and what <hi>alurements</hi> it layed before me, to hide it, keep it cloſe and ſecret.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> Saith my baſe <hi>heart,</hi> You are known to be a great <hi>profeſſor</hi> of <hi>religion,</hi> and if you make it known, you are utterly loſt in the hearts of all that are godly, <hi>for a brother offended is harder to be won, then a ſtrong City,</hi> Prov. <hi>18.19.</hi> you ſhall never be in their affections againe.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> The <hi>name</hi> of <hi>God</hi> will be much <hi>diſhonoured,</hi> you muſt n t tell it in <hi>Gath, nor publiſh it in Askelon, leſt the uncircumciſed blaſpheme: you</hi> need not do it, it is enough you have done it to God.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> The wayes of <hi>God</hi> that you profeſs, which every man (eſpecially the Clergy, which are great enemies to it, and of you in particular) watcheth to have ſomewhat to ſpeak againſt it, and diſhonour it.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> Your own honour, reputation and good name will utterly be loſt and gone, which as the wiſe man ſaith, <hi>Eccl. 7.1. Is better then a precious ointment, better then gold and ſilver,</hi> Prov. <hi>15.15.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> You are now in <hi>a capacity</hi> to do the poor people of God ſome good, but that will utterly ſpoile you for ever.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6.</hi> You will loſe your place, which is your lively-hood. Theſe and many more was my <hi>ſoul</hi> beſet with; and I was taken <hi>captive,</hi> and ſo inſnared, conſulting onely with my baſe heart, that now I ſet my ſelf with all my might to purſue theſe inſtructions, that ſin, my baſe heart, the divel and the world had layed before me, but they all proved <hi>thorns in my ſides, and prickes in my eyes,</hi> Num. <hi>33.55. this covering was too narrow,</hi> it would not ſerve, <hi>Iſa. 28.20.</hi> and ſo I have ſadly found to the <hi>wounding</hi> of my <hi>ſoul,</hi> and by reaſon of <hi>ſin,</hi> and made a ſad <hi>ſpectacle</hi> to men. Oh then I pray precious ſouls beware of ſin!</p>
            <p>Content not your ſelves with the <hi>knowledge</hi> of <hi>Gods wayes,</hi> to make ſome outward <hi>porfeſſion;</hi> that will not go through, that will not <hi>hold out to the end,</hi> and then you will not <hi>receive the crown.</hi> You will fall ſhort of your deſired haven of reſt, <hi>the ſalvation of your ſouls, which is the end of your faith, 1</hi> Pet. <hi>1.9.</hi> Rev. <hi>2.10. 2</hi> Tim. <hi>7.8.</hi> Therefore take our Saviours counſel, <hi>Mat. 12.33. Make the tree good,</hi> look at home into your hearts, and <hi>Purge away all your droſs purely, and throw away all your Tin,</hi> Iſa. <hi>1.25.</hi> for Saints after they come to be Saints, have much droſs in them left, they had reed alwayes be waſhing and purging, <hi>to cleanſe
<pb facs="tcp:166768:4"/> their hearts, and to purifie their inward parts,</hi> Jam. <hi>4.8.</hi> Iſa. <hi>1.17. from an evil conſcience,</hi> H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>b. <hi>10.22.</hi> and it from <hi>dead works,</hi> Heb. <hi>9.14.</hi> and if you ſo do, then you ſhall know how to poſſeſs your veſſels in ſanctification and honour, <hi>1 Theſſ. 4.4.</hi> and be <hi>meet ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified to your maſters uſe, prepared unto every good work, 2</hi> Tim. <hi>2.21.</hi> this <hi>heart</hi>-work, this home-work, is the buſineſs that I have wanted, and I have more wandered abroad, then kept at home: therefore in the firſt place ſweep all clean at home before your own doors, ſet all things right there, or elſe you were even as good ſit ſtill and do nothing, therefore I pray begin there firſt.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2. Cruſh ſin</hi> in the very <hi>beginnings</hi> of it, when it cometh but <hi>darting</hi> into thy thoughts, for they <hi>are evil continually,</hi> Gen. <hi>6.5.</hi> ſuffer it not to abide,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.14.</note> give it no ſpace, no not <hi>a minute,</hi> but withſtand it, when it appears abſtain from it, for there doth evil begin to appear and take place; therefore do you now avoid it by all means, with all ſeed, ſpare it not, <hi>1 Theſſ. 5.22.</hi> for if once your thoughts give but a little harbor to its inticing, you are by it preſently deceived and drawn aſide; and ſin being thus conceived, it bringeth forth. See our firſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and in <hi>David, 2 Sam. 11.2. comp. Gen. 3.5.</hi> What ſad work did ſin make there, which if at firſt it had been narrowly looked into, had been prevented, and therefore <hi>Job,</hi> he will make <hi>a covenant with his eyes,</hi> Job <hi>31.1.</hi> and David he would <hi>take heed to his wayes that he offend not with his tongue,</hi> Pſal. <hi>29.12. He would keep the door of his lips, leſt his heart ſhould be inclined to any evil thing, to practice wicked works with them that work in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquity,</hi> Pſal. <hi>14.14. For the hearr is deceitful above all, and moſt deſperately wicked, and who can know?</hi> therefore have a very great care there, and narrowly watch, <hi>Jer. 17.9.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Take heed of beeing deceived by the <hi>world,</hi> let not <hi>riches, honours, good name, reputation</hi> amongſt men, lead ye to any evil, no not to tell the leaſtly, though you may gaine a world by it, for <hi>God will not be mocked,</hi> Gal. <hi>6.7.</hi> but all things that are done in <hi>ſecret</hi> he <hi>ſeeth,</hi> and there is <hi>nothing</hi> but he <hi>knoweth</hi> it, and will alſo bring it to light: for all <hi>things are naked and open to him that we have to do with,</hi> Heb. <hi>4.13.</hi> and this I know by experience, for all the wayes of darkneſs that I walked in, he did ſee, and all my deeds of darkeneſs he hath brought to light. And I tell you, the <hi>world</hi> with all it's <hi>baits</hi> and <hi>allurements</hi> are very great
<pb facs="tcp:166768:4"/> 
               <hi>ſnares</hi> to your <hi>holy, upright,</hi> and <hi>ſincere walking with God,</hi> and they will if you be not aware ſteal in upon your hearts, ſwell and puffe you up, ſo that you come to be ſurfited and overwhelmed with the cares thereof, and the thoughts of it <hi>pierces you thorow with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny cruelties, 1</hi> Tim. <hi>6.10.</hi> for from that root ſpringeth many ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows and evils: how many have made a very fair and large progreſs toward heaven, but this ſnare hath hindred them and quite ſpoiled them? therefore dearly beloved have a care of this great ſnare the world; this was the laſt, therefore the greateſt and ſtrongeſt argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the divel uſed to Chriſt, <hi>Mat. 4.9. Mat. 19.20, 21. Mark 10.21, 22. Luk. 18.22. Mat. 12.21. Mat. 19.23. Luk. 21.34.36.</hi> alſo was one of my great ſnares.</p>
            <p>I will ſay little more to yoa, for I know you are already, very well taught, only know it is your duty of all other <hi>to walk circumſpectly, not as fools but as wiſe,</hi> Eph. <hi>5.15.</hi> that you are of all others to <hi>be holy, harmeleſs, undefiled, to be ſeparate from</hi> ſin and <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, for holineſs becometh the houſe of God for ever,</hi> Pſal. <hi>93.4.</hi> For he hath taken you to be his people, and you have taken him to be your God, and your God he <hi>is holy, 2</hi> Cor. <hi>6.17, 18. 1</hi> Pet. <hi>1.15, 16.</hi> Levit. <hi>11.4. &amp; 19.2.20.</hi> You know God is not wanting to us, <hi>But hath given us all things appertaining to life and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, 2</hi> Pet. <hi>1.3.</hi> all means to help us forward in our journey towards heaven: he hath given his <hi>word, ſpirit,</hi> his <hi>holy</hi> and good <hi>ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> Nehem. <hi>9.13, 20.</hi> Pſal. <hi>141.19, 20. &amp; 68.11.</hi> and now if we be not wanting to our ſelves, what is it not but we may do?</p>
            <p>But we muſt be doers as well as ſayers and hearers, for there lieth all the happineſs, <hi>bleſſed and happy, ſaith Chriſt, are you that know theſe things and do them.</hi> Therefore let us minde to do all the will of God: and this <hi>David</hi> he was reſolved to do, I will have <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to all thy commandments,</hi> and then I am ſure I ſhall not need to fear any <hi>ſhame,</hi> Pſal. <hi>119.6.</hi> he would as well be <hi>holy</hi> at <hi>home</hi> in his <hi>ſecret cloſet,</hi> as <hi>abroad</hi> in the <hi>publike aſſembly,</hi> and if you do not keep a ſtrict eye there, all will not, nay all cannot be well. O then I pray take theſe few things.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> Be often with God by prayer in ſecret, keep your private watches with your God, <hi>Eph. 6.18. Phil. 3.6. Luk. 21.36. Mat. 6.5.</hi> Study the word of God, meditate on that, <hi>1 Tim. 4.13. 2 Tim. 3.15, 16, 17. Pſal. 1.2. &amp; 119.97, 98, 99, 100.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb facs="tcp:166768:5"/>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 4.29.</note>
               <hi>3.</hi> Avoid all prophane or idle talke and diſcourſe, as <hi>fooliſh jeſting which is not ſeemly, but rather giving of thanks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9.27 2 Cor. 10.5</note>
               <hi>4.</hi> Watch over your inbred luſt, and <hi>beat down and keep un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your bodies, and labour to bring under ſubjection to the obedience of Chriſt every thought.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> Forſake not, but be diligent to frequent the <hi>aſſembly</hi> of the <hi>Saints</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> Heb. <hi>10.25.</hi> Act. <hi>2.42.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6.</hi> Take it kindly and lovingly when the brethren tell or warn any one of you of your faults, let it be <hi>balme to your heads,</hi> Pſal. <hi>141.5.</hi> Prov. <hi>9.8.</hi> but be ſure if you do tell your brethren of their faults or ſins,<note place="margin">Levit. 19.17. Mat. 18.15, 16, 17, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8. 1 Cor. 16.14. Jam. 5.19, 20. 1 Pet. 4.2.2. &amp; 4.8.</note> do it in <hi>love, debate</hi> and <hi>reaſon</hi> the caſe with thy neighbour, and deal with him as with thine own <hi>heart, plainly</hi> and <hi>ſincerely,</hi> and by this means you will and may <hi>ſave a ſoul from death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And laſt of all, have <hi>fervent charity,</hi> for that is the <hi>bond of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,</hi> and all is worth nothing, where this buſineſs of love and charity is wanting, therefore <hi>Holy and beloved, as the Elect of God, put on</hi> (be you clothed with) <hi>bowels of love, mercie, and pity, for love will cover and hide a multitude of ſins, and ſo let all your things be done in love,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>16.14.</hi> And now, <hi>The God of all grace, who hath called you into his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal glory by Chriſt Jeſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jam. 5.20.</note> 
               <hi>after that ye have ſuffered a while, make you perfect, ſtabliſh, ſtrengthen and ſettle you. To him be glory and dominion for ever and ever, Amen, 1</hi> Pet. <hi>10.10.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, not worthy becauſe of my ſins to be reckoned amongſt the godly, Edmund Chillenden.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Fom my houſe in</hi> Coleman-<hi>ſtreet</hi> London, <date>
                     <hi>this this 29 of</hi> Nov. <hi>1643.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Numb. <hi>32.23.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <hi>But if you will not do ſo, ye have ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord, and be ſure your ſin will finde you out.</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:166768:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Rom. 7.13.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Sin is exceeding ſinful.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IN</hi> is of it ſelf an <hi>evil ſickneſs,</hi> or <hi>diſeaſe,</hi> that hath crept into all <hi>mankinde,</hi> ſince the fall, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.18, 19. and it may very fitly be called, the <hi>evil</hi> of <hi>evils,</hi> for the <hi>devils</hi> by reaſon of <hi>ſin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2.4. Job. 8.44. Jude 6. verſ.</note> fell (from being <hi>Angels</hi> of <hi>light,</hi> keeping not their firſt <hi>ſtation,</hi> or <hi>habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi>) to utter <hi>darkneſs,</hi> debarred of that <hi>light, liberty,</hi> and <hi>happineſs,</hi> which they injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, being by reaſon of it thruſt down to <hi>hell;</hi> there being kept in <hi>everlaſting chains under darkneſs of damnation, in that day he will judge the world,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.4. Jude 6.</p>
            <p>Sin filled them full of all <hi>deadly poiſon</hi> and <hi>malice,</hi> and ſo they became <hi>adverſaries</hi> and <hi>enemies</hi> to <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>creatures men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 8.44. Gen. 3.1, 2.</note> therefore he is called <hi>Satan,</hi> Job 1.6. Rev. 20.2. 1 Pet. 5.8. Zech. 3.1. 1 Theſſ. 2.18. <hi>Divel,</hi> Deut. 32.17. <hi>with</hi> 1 Pet. 5.8. <hi>for your adverſary the Devil, as a rouring Lyon walks about ſeeking whom he may devour;</hi> he is very malitious, full of envy,<note place="margin">John 8.44.</note> 
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.1. he is called the <hi>Tempter,</hi> laboring to draw men to ſin, indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring mans ruine and deſtruction, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.3. <hi>A Serpent,</hi> and <hi>Dragon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10.8. 1 Pet. 5.8. Eph. 6.12. Mat 4.3, 9. &amp; 12.46.</note> 
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.19. he and all his <hi>Angels,</hi> full of <hi>malicious venom</hi> and <hi>envy,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>people,</hi> Mat. 10.1. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.12. and all this ſin hath done, for it made him a <hi>divel,</hi> and hath filled him full of all manner of <hi>wicked filthineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore <hi>ſin</hi> is that <hi>deadly poiſon</hi> that contains, and from whence
<pb n="1" facs="tcp:166768:6"/> all other <hi>poiſons</hi> flow and proceed. The Apoſtle <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.21. very fitly ſets it forth, where he calleth it, <hi>filthineſs, and ſuperfluity of naughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs (or abundance) of naughtineſs;</hi> the very <hi>excrements,</hi> or <hi>dung</hi> of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>filthineſs;</hi> the <hi>dreggs</hi> of it, worſe then all, fit for no uſe, <hi>ſtinking,</hi> and <hi>loathſome:</hi> it is <hi>ſin, and out of meaſure ſinful Sin,</hi> moſt <hi>abominable, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable,</hi> and <hi>vile,</hi> to be <hi>abhorred.</hi> Now as it is thus in its own nature, <hi>vile</hi> and <hi>poiſonous,</hi> ſo it cauſes <hi>men,</hi> that it getteth harbor in, to be <hi>filthy</hi> and <hi>poiſonous,</hi> they thereby become unprofitable, uſeleſs, fit for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.3. <hi>They are all gone aſide, they are altogether become filthy, unprofitable, of no uſe,</hi> Job 15.16. ſaith, <hi>man is become abominable filthy (horrible loathſome)</hi> by reaſon of <hi>drinking in this poiſonous ſin,</hi> and <hi>iniquity like water,</hi> Eph. 4.18, 19. with Rom. 3.11. to 19. it hath ſo filled them with the <hi>poiſonous venome,</hi> that the holy Ghoſt compares it to the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of Aſpes,</hi> or <hi>Serpents;</hi> and <hi>men</hi> that are ſo <hi>poiſoned,</hi> are called <hi>Serpents,</hi> Mat. 23.33. <hi>Ye Serpents, and generation of vipers,</hi> Pſal. 58 4. ſpeaking of wicked men, ſaith, <hi>They are estranged from their mothers wombe, they go astray, as ſoon as they be born they ſpeak lies,</hi> and they are of that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomous nature, that he ſaith, <hi>Their poiſon is the poiſon of a Serpent,</hi> Pſal. 140.3. it is called <hi>vomit,</hi> that which is loathſome, <hi>Job</hi> 20.15. and men that ſwallow it down are called <hi>doggs,</hi> Prov. 26.11. 2 Pet. 2.22. Phil. 3.2. Pſal. 22.16, 20. &amp; 59, 6. &amp; 68, 23. <hi>For doggs</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>have compaſſed me about, baſe and vile perſons, filthy men,</hi> ſo made by ſin; <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venouſly diſpoſed wretches,</hi> Rev. 22.15. Mat. 7.6. it is called <hi>mire,</hi> and men are called <hi>Sows or Swine,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.23. for it is of that <hi>poiſonous nature</hi> that it preſently <hi>diſperſes</hi> it ſelf all over the <hi>body,</hi> that it all <hi>beſpots</hi> and <hi>beſmears</hi> the <hi>creature;</hi> and as the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> 1.4, 5. <hi>The whole-heart is ſicke, the whole heart is faint, there is no part free, from the crown of the head to the ſole of the foot, there is no ſoundneſs in it, but wounds, bruiſes,</hi> and <hi>putrifying ſoares.</hi> What ſhall or can be ſaid more? it is called <hi>darkneſs,</hi> Joh. 1.5. &amp; 3.15. 1 Joh. 1.4, 5, 6, &amp; 2.9, 11. <hi>Blindneſs,</hi> Eph. 4.18. <hi>Shame,</hi> Jud. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>3. <hi>nakedneſs,</hi> Rev. 3.18. <hi>folly,</hi> Gen. 34.7. <hi>madneſs.</hi> Pſal. 85.8. Act. 26.11. Luk. 6.7. whatſoever is filthy, naught, deteſtable, or vile, and paineful, ſin is the author and cauſe of.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It will appear to be out of <hi>meaſure ſinful</hi> by the <hi>ſpoile</hi> it hath brought and made on <hi>man;</hi> What a breach did it make at the firſt on our firſt <hi>parents,</hi> Gen. 2.25. compared with <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.27. Eccleſ. 7.29. Gen. 5.1. who were <hi>created righteous,</hi> and <hi>good,</hi> Yea <hi>very good,</hi> Gen. 1.31. in the very <hi>Image</hi> or <hi>likeneſs</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> Eph. 4.24. Col. 3.10. and this made good <hi>David</hi> in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.4, 5.6. ſay, <hi>He had made him little lower then the Angels, thou hast crowned him with honor and glory,</hi> and of the very <hi>creation</hi> and <hi>form</hi> of his <hi>body,</hi> he was <hi>a glorious creature,</hi> Pſal. 139.14. <hi>I will praiſe thee, for I am wonderfully and fearfully made, curiouſly wrought of the earthly mould;</hi> in <hi>rare</hi> and <hi>admirable comelineſs, beauty,</hi> and <hi>proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> with all <hi>ſufficient furniture;</hi> ſo <hi>clad</hi> with <hi>skin</hi> and <hi>fleſh,</hi> and joyned with <hi>bones</hi> and <hi>ſinews,</hi> Job 10.11. that of all his <hi>creatures, man</hi> was his
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:166768:6"/> moſt <hi>glorious</hi> on the <hi>earth,</hi> for to him he <hi>ſubjected,</hi> all other <hi>creatures,</hi> and gave him the <hi>rule</hi> and <hi>dominion</hi> over the <hi>earth</hi> and <hi>ſea,</hi> and all <hi>things therein,</hi> Gen. 1.28. for all the <hi>world</hi> was made for him, even the <hi>glorious Sun, Moon,</hi> and <hi>Stars,</hi> all for his <hi>uſe</hi> and <hi>ſervice,</hi> Deut. 4.19.</p>
            <p>And as he was thus <hi>created</hi> and <hi>made,</hi> ſo he had <hi>ſingular wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>endowments, Will, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> and many <hi>faculties,</hi> all good, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.21. he had <hi>Knowledge, Righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Holineſs,</hi> for <hi>performance</hi> of all <hi>holy duties</hi> to his <hi>Creator,</hi> Gen. 1.27. Col. 3.10. Eccleſ. 7.29, 31. Eph. 4.24.</p>
            <p>But now cometh <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>deveſts</hi> and <hi>ſpoiles</hi> all the <hi>glory</hi> of this <hi>admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable creature</hi> in his firſt and <hi>prime excellencies;</hi> as it ſaid of <hi>Reuben,</hi> he was <hi>Jacobs</hi> firſt <hi>born,</hi> his <hi>might,</hi> the <hi>beginning of his ſtrength,</hi> the <hi>excellency</hi> of <hi>dignity, and the excellency of power,</hi> Deut. 21.17. all this by <hi>ſin,</hi> excellent <hi>Reuben</hi> becometh <hi>weak</hi> as <hi>water,</hi> and ſhould not <hi>excel,</hi> becauſe he <hi>ſinned in going up to his fathers bed;</hi> ſo our firſt <hi>parents</hi> were by <hi>ſin ſpoiled,</hi> for whereas they were <hi>glorious creatures,</hi> fit <hi>companions</hi> for <hi>God,</hi> with whom there was <hi>ſweet fellowſhip</hi> and <hi>communion,</hi> Prov. 8.30. Job 17.5. Job 5.23. yet by it man becometh an <hi>enemy</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> Rom. 8.7. and is <hi>filled full</hi> of all <hi>villany</hi> and <hi>wickedneſs,</hi> yea the very <hi>thoughts of his heart</hi> (Gen. 6 5.) <hi>are evil; and deſperately wicked,</hi> Jer. 17.9. <hi>the minde</hi> is without the <hi>knowledge of God,</hi> the very <hi>conſciences are defiled,</hi> Tit. 1.15. 1 Tim. 4.2. ſo that now they are become <hi>vile, filthy,</hi> and <hi>abominable beaſts,</hi> having <hi>vile affections,</hi> being <hi>fraught</hi> with all <hi>unrighteouſneſs, wickedneſs, maliciouſneſs, wrath, envy, covetouſneſs, inordinate luſt,</hi> being <hi>empty</hi> and <hi>void</hi> of all that is <hi>good,</hi> but <hi>full</hi> of all <hi>poiſonous evils,</hi> Pſal. 81.11. Prov. 1.25, 30. Iſa. 28.12. Rom. 1.2, 9. Mat. 12.44. Pſal. 36.1. fit <hi>companions</hi> for none but the <hi>divel</hi> and his <hi>Angels,</hi> Mat. 25.41. <hi>Go ye curſed in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> everlasting fire prepared for the divel and his angels;</hi> for <hi>doggs, ſwine,</hi> and ſuch like <hi>creatures,</hi> Rev. 22.15. for as <hi>ſin</hi> made the <hi>Angels divels,</hi> ſo it hath made men of the <hi>nature</hi> of <hi>divels,</hi> therefore our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſaith to the <hi>Jews, You are of your father the divel, whoſe children you are,</hi> Joh. 8.44. and he called <hi>Judas a divel,</hi> Joh. 6.70. <hi>have not I choſen twelve of you, and one of you is a divel?</hi> This havock hath ſin made.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Sin</hi> maketh a man a <hi>ſervant,</hi> yea a <hi>ſlave</hi> not only to it <hi>ſelf,</hi> Rom. 6.20. <hi>ſervants of ſin,</hi> but <hi>ver.</hi> 19. to <hi>uncleanneſs,</hi> unto <hi>iniquity,</hi> Tit 3.3 <hi>to be fooliſh, diſobedient, deceived, ſerving divers lusts and pleaſures, living in malice</hi> and <hi>envy, hateful, and hating one another.</hi> What a <hi>ſlave</hi> was <hi>Sampſon</hi> to his <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilah,</hi> Judges 19.4, 15. How did <hi>he ſerve her? he</hi> was <hi>her</hi> very <hi>ſlave,</hi> he parted with his <hi>great</hi> and <hi>glorious ſtrength,</hi> and <hi>excellency;</hi> he <hi>diſcovered</hi> to <hi>her his</hi> very <hi>heart,</hi> Judges 16.17. <hi>And it came to paſs when ſhe preſſed him daily with her words, and urged him, that his ſoul was vexed unto death, and told her all his heart,</hi> which was his ruine. What is it that man will not do, to be a <hi>ſervant</hi> and <hi>ſlave to ſin,</hi> to <hi>ſerve</hi> one <hi>baſe luſt</hi> or other? what a <hi>ſlave</hi> was <hi>David</hi> to his <hi>Bathſheba?</hi> how did he <hi>travel</hi> to <hi>ſerve,</hi> and be a <hi>ſlave</hi> to his <hi>luſt,</hi> that he might <hi>obtaine</hi> it, and to carry it <hi>ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly?</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:166768:7"/> 2 Sam. 11.2. to 18.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Sin</hi> bringeth <hi>ſhame,</hi> Rom. 6.21. <hi>For it is a ſhame</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>to ſpeak of thoſe things that are done of them in ſecret,</hi> Eph. 5.12. but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>ſin</hi> came, <hi>man</hi> could look <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>face</hi> with <hi>boldneſs,</hi> and not be <hi>aſhamed,</hi> Gen. 2.25. <hi>And they were both naked, the man and his wife, and were not aſhamed,</hi> but ſo ſoon as <hi>ſin</hi> had taken hold on him, he ſeeth his <hi>nakedneſs,</hi> and ſo is <hi>aſhamed.</hi> Exod. 22.25. the people commit a <hi>ſin in worſhiping the molten calfe, Moſes ſeeth their nakedneſs;</hi> for <hi>Aaron</hi> hade had made them naked unto their <hi>ſhame amongſt their enemies,</hi> Hoſ. 2.3. Rev. 3.17. &amp; 16.15. this was the cauſe, that poor <hi>Laodicea</hi> was ſo <hi>poor, miſerable, blinde, and naked,</hi> becauſe ſhe had <hi>ſinned,</hi> was <hi>lukewarm</hi> in the matters of <hi>God, neither hot nor cold, ſin</hi> had ſo <hi>ſpoiled</hi> her, and made her <hi>miſerable ſhameful.</hi> God he threatens <hi>Iſrael</hi> for their <hi>ſins,</hi> Deut. 28.48. that they ſhould <hi>ſerve their enemies in hunger, thirſt, and naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to their ſhame,</hi> for indeed <hi>ſhame</hi> and <hi>confuſion</hi> is the <hi>fruit</hi> of <hi>ſin,</hi> Iſa. 65.13. where ſuch as were <hi>not ſinful</hi> ſhould <hi>rejoyce,</hi> but <hi>ſinners</hi> they <hi>ſhould be aſhamed,</hi> even <hi>all that truſt in graven Images,</hi> they ſhall be <hi>turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed back, they ſhall be greatly aſhamed,</hi> Iſa. 42.17. Dan. 9.7, 8, 9. <hi>A wound and diſhonour, a ſhame, ſuch as ſhall not be wiped away; ſuch a reproach as will ſtick,</hi> for they do not know <hi>whither to cauſe their ſhame to go,</hi> 2 Sam. 13.13. compared Prov. 6.33.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Sin</hi> maketh <hi>man accurſed,</hi> yea it hath cauſed <hi>a curſe</hi> to come on all <hi>creatures,</hi> for they are all <hi>brought under bondage, curſe</hi> and <hi>ſlavery,</hi> Gen. 3.17. <hi>Curſed is the ground for thy ſake, thorns and thiſtles ſhall it bring forth; in the ſweat of thy face ſhall thou eat bread, till thou return to the duſt,</hi> Rom. 8.20. <hi>For the creature was made ſubject to vanity, and the whole creation groaneth and travelleth in pain until now.</hi> It is <hi>ſin</hi> onely that hath cauſed this, and where it is <hi>entertained,</hi> there is no <hi>bleſſing</hi> to be expected, but a curſing; for he that <hi>hideth, huggeth,</hi> and <hi>loveth ſin, ſhall not proſper,</hi> Prov. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>8.13. but he ſhall be <hi>curſed</hi> in his very <hi>bleſſings,</hi> Mal. 2.2. for <hi>God</hi> and <hi>ſin</hi> is at <hi>mortal enmity,</hi> Rom. 8.7. <hi>To be carnally</hi> (ſinfully) <hi>minded is death, for it is enmity against God, for it is not ſubject to the law of God, neither can it;</hi> for it will alwayes be like the divel, oppoſing of <hi>God,</hi> and ſtriving to be above, and therefore where this enemy <hi>ſin</hi> is entertained, <hi>God</hi> moſt and will <hi>ſet his face againſt that man,</hi> Levit. 17.10, 20, 3. Ezek. 14.8. as his mortal enemy, that harbors ſo arch a rebel to his <hi>crown</hi> and <hi>dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> as ſin is, for <hi>God</hi> hateth it, <hi>loaths it,</hi> and cannot endure it, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.25. He there ſpeaking to the <hi>Church of Pergamos,</hi> though he did love her, and commended her for many good things that were found in her, but her <hi>ſins</hi> he could not endure, and ſaith, <hi>Thou haſt them that hold the Doctrine of the Nicolaitans, which thing I hate;</hi> his <hi>Soul</hi> did <hi>abhor</hi> ſuch a <hi>people,</hi> Deut. 32.19. Levit. 26.30. Pſal. 78.59. <hi>He was wrath and greatly abhorred Iſrael, for they had provoked him to anger with their high places, and moved him to jealouſie with their graven Images: therefore he was wrath, and greatly abhorred Iſrael,</hi> that were before his beloved people under
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:166768:7"/> 
               <hi>bleſſings</hi> and <hi>mercies,</hi> but their <hi>ſins</hi> brought all theſe curſes on them, as may appear by theſe Scriptures, <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.26, 28. &amp; 29, 19, 30.1. <hi>Joſhua</hi> 6.18. <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.15. &amp; 29, 20, 21, 27. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34 24. <hi>Heb</hi> 6.8. <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.15. to 26. <hi>The curſe of the Lord is in the houſe of the wicked,</hi> Pro. 3.33. and nothing ſhall proſper he undertaketh, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.4, 6. &amp; 35.5. Prov. 11.7. <hi>the very hope of the unjuſt man periſheth,</hi> Hoſ. 13.3. and this is the ſtate of <hi>a ſinner,</hi> that while ſin <hi>rules</hi> and <hi>reigns</hi> in their <hi>mortal bodies,</hi> they do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but <hi>delight</hi> in the <hi>curſed</hi> works of <hi>darkeneſs,</hi> which they are <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed</hi> to bring to light, that let him turn which way he will, ſtill <hi>curſes</hi> and <hi>plagues</hi> attend him, <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.15. to 26. it makes <hi>a man a horror</hi> and an <hi>abomination,</hi> or <hi>hated of his neighbor,</hi> Prov. 29.27. compared Prov. 14.17. <hi>A man of wicked devices is hated,</hi> 2 Sam. 13.22. for <hi>Abſolom</hi> hated <hi>Amnon,</hi> becauſe he had forced his ſiſter <hi>Tamar,</hi> he had <hi>wrought a wicked device,</hi> and therefore was <hi>abhorred</hi> by him.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Sin</hi> it <hi>robs</hi> and <hi>ſpoileth a man of God,</hi> Iſa. 59.2. <hi>Your iniquities have ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated between you and your God, and your ſins have hid his face from you.</hi> This people in the 58 Chapter had been a faſting and humbling their ſouls, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.3. and they aske a reaſon why God was not found of them, and that he did not anſwer them, they <hi>expostulate</hi> the caſe with <hi>God: Wherefore have we afflicted our ſouls, and thou takeſt no knowledge? where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare have we faſted, and thou ſeeſt not?</hi> God giveth them the reaſon in the fourth verſe, it was their <hi>ſins</hi> and their <hi>iniquities</hi> that had <hi>robbed</hi> and <hi>deprived</hi> them of the <hi>good things</hi> that they might have enjoyed, ſo ſaith the Lord by the Prophet, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.25. <hi>Your iniquities have turned away</hi> (put by, robbed, deprived you of) <hi>theſe things, and your ſins have withholden</hi> (by force and violence, as a company of robbers do) <hi>good things from you; for behold you faſt for ſtrife and debate, to ſmite with the fiſt of wickedneſs, to adde drunkenneſs to thirſt,</hi> Deut. 29.19. it was to feed, ſupport, and to make proviſion for <hi>ſin, to ſpend it on their luſt,</hi> therefore they <hi>asked and did not receive, becauſe they asked amiſs,</hi> Jam. 4.3. it was to take care for the <hi>Arch-rebell</hi> and <hi>traiterous enemy</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> and while <hi>ſin</hi> is nigh and is nouriſhed, ſuccoured and harbored, <hi>God</hi> he will be far off, <hi>for God is far from the wicked and ungodly ſinners,</hi> Eph. 2.12, 13. who are ſaid to be <hi>without God in the world, far off, being enemies,</hi> aliens, or ſtrangers <hi>to God,</hi> and by ſins made to be at <hi>enmity in their mindes by wicked works,</hi> Col. 1.21. quite <hi>robbed</hi> and <hi>ſpoiled</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and all that was <hi>God-like,</hi> and filled full of all <hi>deadly poiſon;</hi> ſo that his heart is ſo ſwoln with it, that he ſaith there is <hi>no god,</hi> Pſal. 14.1. <hi>He is not once in all their thoughts,</hi> Pſal. 10.4. but abound in all villany and miſchiefes, <hi>Being filled with all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs, fornication, wickedneſs, covetouſneſs, maliciouſneſs, full of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, murther, debate, deceit, malignity, backbiters, haters of good, without un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding,</hi> Rom. 1.29, 30, 31. compared with <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.21. Tit. 3.3. Eph. 2.2, 3. So that we may ſee by this what ſpoile ſin hath made, quite rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed and ſpoiled us of God; what ſpoile did it make on our <hi>parents,</hi> as is partly before minded? How did the <hi>Lord rejoyce in the works be had
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:166768:8"/> made,</hi> Gen. 1.31. compare verſ. 4. both with Pſal. 104.31. &amp; Prov. 8.31. ſeeing the <hi>order, comlineſs,</hi> and <hi>beauty</hi> that was in all his <hi>works,</hi> they were <hi>good,</hi> agreeable to his <hi>will,</hi> they pleaſed him, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.4. <hi>for every creature of God is good,</hi> pleaſant, ſweet, profitable, cauſing joy, <hi>Song</hi> 1.2. &amp; 4.10. Deut. 6.11. 1 Sam. 9.2. Gen. 24.16. compare Mark. 9.42. &amp; Luk. 17.2. <hi>And the Lord did rejoyce in the habitable part of his earth,</hi> Prov. 8.31. great <hi>peace</hi> was between <hi>God</hi> and <hi>man,</hi> yea and all the <hi>creatures,</hi> all the <hi>works</hi> that <hi>God</hi> had <hi>made,</hi> they did <hi>praiſe him,</hi> and gave <hi>him honor,</hi> Pſal. 45.10. <hi>When the morning ſtars ſang togather, and all the ſons of God ſhout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for joy,</hi> Pſal. 148.3. Job 1.6. there was no <hi>diviſion</hi> or <hi>variance,</hi> no <hi>hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſpirits</hi> againſt <hi>God</hi> or <hi>man</hi> to <hi>work</hi> or do him any miſchief; no <hi>death</hi> or <hi>diſeaſes,</hi> no <hi>fear</hi> of <hi>guilt</hi> to torment and afflict the <hi>ſoul</hi> of <hi>man,</hi> nor any <hi>noiſome poiſonous luſt</hi> to <hi>rebell</hi> in their <hi>bodies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now cometh <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>robs</hi> us of all this, and <hi>fills</hi> the <hi>whole creation</hi> with <hi>miſchief, ſtrife,</hi> and <hi>debate,</hi> layeth or turneth the whole <hi>world</hi> into, or in <hi>wickedneſs,</hi> 1 Joh. 5.19.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Sin</hi> cauſeth <hi>ſorrow</hi> in <hi>God,</hi> and it <hi>grieveth</hi> his <hi>ſpirit,</hi> Gen. 6.3, 5. <hi>The wickedneſs of man was great in the earth, and the very imaginations of the thoughts of his heart were wholly evil,</hi> every, or <hi>all the day,</hi> that they care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully minded their hearts for evil alwayes, therefore <hi>It repented God that he had made man, and it grieved him at the very heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To ſee that man, that he had made ſo <hi>goodly</hi> and <hi>comely a creature, cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated</hi> him after his own <hi>Image,</hi> or <hi>likeneſs,</hi> Gen. 1.27. &amp; 15.1. ſhould ſo <hi>ſin</hi> againſt him, and <hi>provoke him,</hi> not onely at the <hi>firſt</hi> in <hi>Edens garden,</hi> for which he might for ever have left them in <hi>miſery,</hi> and utterly have caſt them off, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 75.3. was pleaſed now in the <hi>midſt</hi> of <hi>Judgement,</hi> to <hi>remember mercy,</hi> Hab. 3.2. and to provide a <hi>Saviour</hi> for them, and <hi>to lay their help upon one that was mighty,</hi> Pſal. 89.19. Yea then when they were <hi>all turned aſide, and gone out of the way,</hi> Pſal. 14.2, 3, 4. compare Iſa. 59.15, 16, 17. &amp; 63.5. <hi>He then looked down from heaven, to ſee if any underſtood God, if there were any judgement, but he ſaw no interceſſor; there was none to uphold, therefore his own arme of righteouſneſs that upheld, and wrought ſalvation,</hi> and put all things in <hi>a right</hi> and <hi>orderly frame,</hi> bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us back <hi>to Chriſt, the Shepherd and keeper of our ſouls,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.25. this now doth <hi>grieve God,</hi> that after ſo much <hi>love</hi> and <hi>mercy,</hi> man that he had ſo done by, taken ſo much <hi>paines</hi> withall, that had <hi>ſpared</hi> no coſt, <hi>no not his own Son,</hi> Rom. 8 32. <hi>but gave him to dye, and ſhed his blood to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem them from their vaine converſations they had received from the tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their fathers,</hi> Gen. 3.15 compare 1 Pet. 1.18, 19. and all, that <hi>man</hi> might become <hi>obedient</hi> and <hi>ſubject</hi> to <hi>God</hi> to do his will as he hath <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded us,</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.23.</p>
            <p>To this end he gave them his <hi>word</hi> and <hi>oracles,</hi> Pſal. 147.19, 20. Pſal. 2.7. Exo. 21.1. Rom. 9.4, 5. to inſtruct them how they ſhould walk towards him, <hi>In all well-pleaſingneſs,</hi> Heb. 13.21. <hi>he gave them right judgements and true Laws, good Statutes and Commandments,</hi> he had ſo <hi>great a deſire</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:166768:8"/> after their <hi>good,</hi> that he himſelf <hi>cometh down upon the mount, and ſpeaks to them from heaven,</hi> Nehe. 9.13. Pſal. 68.11. Nevertheleſs ſuch preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency had ſin in them, <hi>That they diſobyed him, and rebelled againſt him, and caſt all his good Laws behinde their backs,</hi> 1 King. 9.10. <hi>hated God,</hi> and to be <hi>reformed,</hi> Pſal. 50.17. Ezek. 23.35. <hi>ſhew his prophets, that teſtified againſt them to return, wrought great provocation,</hi> Neh. 9.26. Jer. 32.31, 32. compare 1 Kings 23.26. <hi>though he gave them his good ſpirit to inſtruct them, guide and lead them,</hi> Gen. 6.3. compare Nehem. 9.20. Num. 11.17. <hi>in the good, old, and holy way, wherein they ſhould finde reſt for their ſouls,</hi> wooing and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending</hi> with them, <hi>diſputing</hi> and <hi>convincing</hi> them, by the mouths of his <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>ſervants,</hi> in and by the <hi>word</hi> of his <hi>grace;</hi> alſo by <hi>inward motions,</hi> and <hi>checks</hi> of <hi>conſcience;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet nothing would do, for the <hi>ſtrong man kept the houſe,</hi> ſin had got poſſeſſion, <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.21, 22. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.29. <hi>Mark</hi> 3.37. that they <hi>rebelled againſt him, and vexed his holy ſpirit, therefore he was turned to be their enemy, and fought againſt them,</hi> Exod. 15.24. Numb. 14.11. Acts 7.15. Job 30.21. Jer. 30.14. Judges 14.15. compare Eph. 4.29, 30. &amp; 5.11, 12.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Sin</hi> hinders and <hi>cloggs prayer,</hi> though they be never ſo <hi>long,</hi> and be <hi>uttered</hi> never ſo <hi>loud,</hi> they go not <hi>upward</hi> toward <hi>heaven,</hi> they <hi>aſcend not,</hi> but do <hi>remaine</hi> here below, they are rejected of <hi>God,</hi> as <hi>Caines ſacrifice was,</hi> Gen. 4.3, 4, 5. he will not hear in <hi>heaven;</hi> for he is <hi>deaf,</hi> and his <hi>ear</hi> is by ſin <hi>made heavy,</hi> Iſa. 59.1. compare Prov. 1.28, 29, 30, 31. <hi>though they call upon him, he will not hear them, though they ſeek him early, yet they ſhall not finde him;</hi> and the reaſon is rendered, <hi>For they hated knowledge, and did not chuſe the fear of the Lord, they would none of his councel, they deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſed all his reproofs,</hi> Pſal. 81.11, 12. <hi>therefore it ſhall</hi> and will <hi>be ill with them that are wicked, for the reward of their hands ſhall be given unto them,</hi> Iſa. 3.11.</p>
            <p>This <hi>David</hi> knew very well, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.18. <hi>If I regard iniquity in my heart, the Lord will not hear me,</hi> as if the Prophet ſhould have ſaid, If I regard, hug, and make much of my ſin, delight and take pleaſure in it, <hi>God</hi> will not regard me, ſaith he. This the <hi>Iews,</hi> as <hi>wicked</hi> as they were, knew well enough, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 9.31. <hi>Now we know God heareth not ſinners, but if any man be a worſhipper of God and do his will, him be heareth,</hi> Jam. 5.15, 16. 1 Joh. 5.14. <hi>the prayer of the wicked is ſin, his ſacrifice is a great abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination to the Lord;</hi> he cannot endure it, he loaths both it and them, <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.8, 29. with <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.27. <hi>How much more when he bringeth it with an evil,</hi> wicked ſinful mind, being alienated and made ſtrangers from <hi>God in their mindes, by wicked and ſinful works,</hi> Eph. 2.12. Col. 1.21. Tit. 3.3. <hi>for what hope hath the hypocrite? will the Lord hear his cry?</hi> Job. 27.8, 9. <hi>No, he is far from the wicked,</hi> Prov. 15.29. <hi>When they ſpread forth their hands, God he will not hear them, he will hide his eyes from them, and when they make many prayers, God will not have regard, their hands are full of blood,</hi> Iſa. 1.15. therefore he <hi>loatheth their new Moons and their Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths, their ſolemn aſſemblies; his ſoul hated them,</hi> they were <hi>a trouble to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:166768:9"/> him, he was weary of bearing them,</hi> Iſa. 66.3. This the Church crieth out of, and ſadly bewaileth, <hi>Lam.</hi> 4.44. that becauſe of her ſins, <hi>God he hod covered himſelf with a cloud, that her prayers ſhould not paſs thorow.</hi> O what a loſs is the poor Church in now! God <hi>he hath hid his face, and ſhe is much troubled,</hi> Pſal. 30.7. Whereas ſhe was wont by prayer to <hi>ride</hi> and <hi>ſoar aloft;</hi> they were her <hi>Chariots</hi> and <hi>horſes,</hi> by which ſhe <hi>pierced</hi> the <hi>heavens, and went with boldneſs to the throne of grace,</hi> Heb. 4.16. and received <hi>bleſſings</hi> from thence both ſpiritual and temporal, but now ſhe is debarred all by ſin; that puts a ſtop to every good thing, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. 1 Tim. 4.8. &amp; 6.6. Jer. 5.25.</p>
            <p n="8">8. It breaks the peace and bleſſed communion of the Church of God.</p>
            <p>The Churches of Chriſt are a holy people called out of the world by the <hi>good word</hi> of his <hi>grace,</hi> they being <hi>begotten againe, purged</hi> and <hi>cleanſed</hi> from all <hi>uncleanneſs</hi> and unholineſs, made <hi>pure by the waſhing of water by the word,</hi> Eph. 5.26, 27. <hi>of his own will,</hi> Jam. 1.18. <hi>not of corruptible ſeed, but of incorruptible by the word of God,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.23. <hi>called to be Saints,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.2. to walk together in a holy <hi>communion</hi> amongſt themſelves, for the worſhip and ſervice of God, and they are called <hi>A ſpiritual houſe, a holy prieſthood to offer up ſpiritual ſacrifices acceptable to God through Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.5. <hi>and therefore are called a holy nation, a choſen genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a royal prieſthood, a peculiar people, that they ſhould ſhew forth the praiſes of him who hath called them out of darkneſs into his marvelous light,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.8. and they may not ſuffer any <hi>unclean</hi> or <hi>unholy perſon</hi> to come in and be of <hi>fellowſhip</hi> with them, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 52.11. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.27. 2 Cor. 6.17. for all that are to <hi>draw neer to God, and bear his veſſel, are to be clean and holy, for holineſs becomes his houſe for ever,</hi> Pſal. 93.5. for his way is <hi>holy,</hi> and the <hi>polluted ſinners</hi> may not enter into it, they will <hi>defile</hi> his <hi>Sanctuary</hi> and <hi>holy things,</hi> Iſa. 35.8. compare Numb. 19.20, 22. Ezek. 28.22. for ſin is <hi>a contagious leproſie,</hi> that will preſently <hi>diffuſe</hi> it ſelf through the whole <hi>body,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>A little leaven leaveneth the whole lump,</hi> 1 Cor. 5.6, 7. therefore when ſin doth appear, they are preſently to labour to <hi>purge themſelves of it</hi> according to the <hi>rule</hi> and <hi>command of Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> that they may be <hi>a holy lumpe;</hi> and this muſt be done in <hi>love,</hi> with all <hi>meekneſs</hi> and lowlineſs of ſpirit, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1, 2. with all <hi>faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs,</hi> without any <hi>partiality, favour,</hi> or <hi>affection,</hi> but where ſin is, there tell the ſinner <hi>plainly of it,</hi> Levit. 19.17. that ſo they may come to ſee their ſins, and bring their <hi>ſacrifice,</hi> that by <hi>repentance</hi> and <hi>forſaking</hi> they may <hi>finde mercy</hi> and ſo <hi>proſper,</hi> Levit. 4.23.28. the <hi>Church</hi> being careful of this, they <hi>walk ſweetly,</hi> and there is a very <hi>comely order</hi> amongſt them, they are, <hi>Song.</hi> 6.4, <hi>comely as Jeruſalem,</hi> Pſal. 4.1, 2, 3. <hi>Fair in ſituation, the joy of the whole earth, the City of the great King.</hi> Now ſin hath in the night crept in, and there having got footing, hath and doth mar al this glory,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:166768:9"/> and utterly diſſipates all the <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>lovelineſſe</hi> which was once theirs, what by <hi>falſe teachers</hi> who do ariſe in and amongſt the <hi>Churches, ſpeaking perverſe things, Act.</hi> 20.30. <hi>bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in damnable errors, even denying the Lord that bought them,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. and alſo often times the frailties of the <hi>Saints</hi> defiles their <hi>bodies</hi> and <hi>ſouls,</hi> by reaſon of ſin,<note place="margin">This my ſin hath cauſed.</note> that the <hi>enemies</hi> without take occaſion to <hi>blaſpheme,</hi> and the <hi>brethren</hi> within are often <hi>ſcandalized</hi> and <hi>grieved:</hi> The <hi>Churches</hi> in the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> daies had woful <hi>experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> of the ſad <hi>work</hi> and <hi>ſpoil ſin</hi> did make amongſt them; look on <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth</hi> how they were <hi>infeſted,</hi> and <hi>Galatia, Philippi,</hi> that they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved <hi>to another Goſpel;</hi> ſee in the ſeven <hi>Churches of Aſia, Rev.</hi> 2.3. <hi>chap.</hi> and there you ſhall find ſin eating out the very <hi>heart</hi> and <hi>life</hi> of <hi>God</hi> amongſt the <hi>Churches,</hi> for amongſt them were bitter <hi>envyings, ſtrife,</hi> and <hi>reproach;</hi> that as the Prophet <hi>ſaith, Every man hunted his brother with a net,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Philip.</hi> 1.15.16. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.11.12.13.</note> 
               <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.1.2. thoſe that were their guides they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came <hi>vain talkers, and deceivers of the minds of the ſimple,</hi> even to the <hi>ſubverting of whole houſes, Tit.</hi> 2.10.11. <hi>teaching things which they ought not for filthy lucre ſake,</hi> ſo that nothing but <hi>rottenneſs</hi> and <hi>putrifaction</hi> did appear, <hi>Iſay</hi> 1.2.3.4.5. <hi>the grace of God turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to wantonneſs,</hi> the <hi>holy liberty</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel made a cloak of malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, Iude</hi> 4. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.16. and all manner of <hi>filthineſs,</hi> ſo that <hi>iniquity was eſtabliſhed</hi> amongſt them <hi>by a Law, Rev.</hi> 2.4.5.14.15.20.21.22.23. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.15. to 20. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 94.20. and ſo come to have their faces made <hi>harder then a ſtone, Ier.</hi> 5.3. hated, to be rebuked and <hi>reformed, Pſalm</hi> 50.16.17. and admit of no reproof, <hi>but harden their necks againſt it, Pro.</hi> 29.1.</p>
            <p>Now the <hi>godly,</hi> whoſe <hi>hearts</hi> are <hi>upright,</hi> and who have <hi>kept their garments clean,</hi> and have not been led <hi>aſide to run in their pernicious wayes,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.2. <hi>that have not known the depths of Satan,</hi> they cannot indure ſuch things, but muſt <hi>teſtifie</hi> and bear their <hi>witneſs</hi> againſt them, and <hi>avoid them, having no fellowſhip with the works of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but to reprove them,</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">But ſtill according to rule in love and pity, Mat. <hi>18.16.17.18. 1</hi> Cor. <hi>16.14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.11. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.24. and now by this means the peace, quiet, and <hi>ſweet Communion</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> cometh to be broken,<note n="†" place="margin">This my ſin alſo hath cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</note> for there cannot be any <hi>fellowſhip with light and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Chriſt and Belial, the believer and the Infidel, or unbeliever,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.15.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sin</hi> wounds the <hi>heart, ſoul,</hi> and <hi>conſcience,</hi> it makes great ſpoyl there, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.10. David <hi>he had committed ſin in numbring the people,</hi> and as ſoon as he had done, <hi>his ſoul was wounded, his heart ſmote him, and he crieth out, Lord I have ſinned greatly in this that I have done, for I have done very fooliſhly,</hi> 1 <hi>Chro.</hi> 21.9. That upon this there cometh a great <hi>cloud,</hi> and <hi>diſmal darkneſs</hi> is <hi>drawn</hi> over the <hi>ſoul, Pſalm</hi> 38.6. great <hi>trouble bowing down</hi> and <hi>cruſhing,</hi> that ſo <hi>all the day long</hi> there is nothing but ſadneſs, and gloomineſs, heavineſs, and <hi>mourning, Pſalm</hi> 35.14. <hi>bowing down heavily:</hi> Now the <hi>arrows of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:166768:10"/> the Almighty take hold,</hi> and they <hi>ſtick faſt, Job</hi> 6.4. <hi>the terrors of God</hi> do now <hi>ſet themſelves in array,</hi> and <hi>drink up the very ſpirit,</hi> and make it like a <hi>parched and dried Heath,</hi> and the <hi>face of God now cometh to be withdrawn, and he hides his loving kindneſs, Pſalm</hi> 88.14. <hi>compared with Jer.</hi> 16.5. that maketh them cry out, <hi>Lord where are thy loving kindneſſes, Pſalm</hi> 89.49. the <hi>horror</hi> of the <hi>Lords wrath</hi> poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes them, and is as <hi>fire in their bones</hi> that <hi>conſumes them,</hi> that they have no <hi>rest,</hi> for their <hi>iniquities do daily go over their heads, Pſalm</hi> 38: 4. <hi>they are heavier then they are able to bear,</hi> the <hi>curſes of the Law they</hi> now begin to terrifie, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.11. <hi>becauſe of tranſgreſſion, and not obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his voice,</hi> now they cry for grief of heart, their ſoul is ſad; we look for <hi>Judgment,</hi> yea for <hi>Salvation,</hi> but it is far from us, becauſe our <hi>ſins</hi> are many, and our <hi>tranſgreſſions</hi> are without <hi>number, Pſalm</hi> 32.4, <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay</hi> 59.11.12. ſo we become <hi>a burthen</hi> to our <hi>ſelves,</hi> and we ſpeak in the <hi>anguiſh of our ſpirit, Job</hi> 7.11. <hi>and complain in the bitterneſs</hi> of our <hi>ſouls;</hi> left <hi>comfortleſs, deſolate,</hi> and <hi>caſt down, our ſalvation paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed away, and clean gone, Job</hi> 30.15.16. the daies of affliction have ceaſed and taken hold on us, we become <hi>a reproach</hi> to the <hi>wicked</hi> and <hi>ungodly,</hi> becauſe of our <hi>wickedneſs</hi> they <hi>laugh</hi> and <hi>blaſpheme;</hi> the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel</hi> he <hi>triumphs</hi> and doth <hi>inſult,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.14. <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.10. ceaſes not to <hi>accuſe us night and day before God in heaven;</hi> our former <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance,</hi> our <hi>familiar friends,</hi> yea our <hi>natural kindred,</hi> and our <hi>brethren,</hi> they <hi>withdraw,</hi> and are <hi>aſhamed of us;</hi> this ſpoyl doth ſin make on a ſoul, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 38.11.</p>
            <p>I have here ſaid ſomewhat of ſin, and the ſpoyl it maketh, and hath made on man, yet not the hundredth part that might be ſaid, I ſhall now ſhew you what ſpoyl it hath made on my ſelf.</p>
            <p>For what hath been ſaid, <hi>ſin</hi> hath <hi>wrath</hi> in <hi>me,</hi> and much more, for as the <hi>Apoſtle ſaith, I have been carnal, and ſold under ſin, Rom.</hi> 7.14. that as the wiſe man <hi>ſaith,</hi> In the <hi>daies of my vanity I have not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held the deſire of mine eys, nor my heart from any joy, Eccleſ.</hi> 2.10. And I have been <hi>compaſſed about</hi> with the <hi>iniquities of my heels, Pſalm</hi> 49.5. <hi>For in me, that is in my fleſh, there dwelleth no good thing, Rom.</hi> 7.18. <hi>O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliver me from the body of this death.</hi> I bleſs God I can ſay with our good Apoſtle, <hi>ver.</hi> 25. <hi>I thank God through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord,</hi> that by him, and through the <hi>riches of Gods love,</hi> I had gotten in ſome meaſure the <hi>victory of the ſins of my youth, Epheſ.</hi> 2.4.5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.37. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 25.7. and with all my might endeavour'd after the wayes of God, but happily I looked in the firſt place too ſoon to the outward <hi>holineſs,</hi> and like <hi>Jehu,</hi> purſued it very eagerly, ſo that in my heart I ſaid, <hi>Come ſee my zeal;</hi> for God, for Chriſt, his wayes and people, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 10.16. and had not quite mortified thoſe <hi>inbred luſts and evil concupiſcenſe,</hi> which <hi>ſin</hi> had wrought in me, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Apoſtles counſel, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.5. I ſhould have then known how to have <hi>poſſeſſed my veſſel in ſanctification and honor,</hi> but becauſe of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:166768:10"/> this the Lord hath been pleaſed to <hi>write</hi> many <hi>bitter things against me,</hi> and hath <hi>made me to poſſeſs the iniquities of my youth, Job.</hi> 13.26. to lye down in <hi>ſhame,</hi> and <hi>confuſion to cover me, becauſe I have ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord, Jer.</hi> 3.25. the <hi>dregs</hi> of the <hi>old man</hi> were ſtill alive, and not put off, there was the remainder of ſin kept and <hi>ſpared,</hi> which have been like as the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> were to <hi>Iſrael, pricks in my eyes, and thorns in my ſide,</hi> to be a continual plague to me, <hi>Numb.</hi> 33.55. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.19.20. which if the <hi>old man, concerning my former converſation, which was corrupt, according to the deceiptful luſt, Epheſ.</hi> 4.22. had been quite ſubdued, and all <hi>deſtroyed,</hi> they had not now <hi>ſcourged</hi> me like the <hi>pricking brier, and grieving thorn, Ezec.</hi> 28.24. compared with <hi>Joſh.</hi> 23.13.</p>
            <p>There were <hi>ſpots</hi> that were left in my <hi>garments,</hi> which wanted waſhing out, which ſome <hi>labour</hi> would have ſoon <hi>diſpatched;</hi> but they being but <hi>ſpots</hi> they were not minded, and my falſe <hi>heart</hi> flattering me all was <hi>well, ſo long as it was ſecret and unknown, though with my heart I utter'd perverſe things; Pro.</hi> 23.33. <hi>I was ſtricken, and yet not ſick, they beat me, and I felt it not,</hi> I lay very ſecure in the midſt of my great danger, <hi>and have been drawn away with the wicked, and with the workers of iniquity,</hi> and yet it hath <hi>ſpoken peace</hi> to me, as to its <hi>neighbour,</hi> but it brought forth <hi>miſchief, Pſalm</hi> 48.3. <hi>For as with a dart it hath ſtricken me through the liver, caſting me down wounded, and have been ſlaine, Prov.</hi> 7.23.26. <hi>and knew not that it was for my life,</hi> by which I have gotten <hi>a wound and a diſhonor,</hi> yea a <hi>reproach that cannot be wiped away, Pro.</hi> 6.33. <hi>knowing not whither to cauſe my ſhame to go,</hi> for I have been <hi>as one of the fools in Iſrael,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.13. Thus ſin compaſſed me about, and got my feet intan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled in its net; after I was <hi>thus wounded,</hi> and caſt <hi>down,</hi> then I did endeavour to get out of the <hi>jawes of death,</hi> and to aſcend from the <hi>chambers of the dead,</hi> that I might <hi>take hold on the paths of life, Pro.</hi> 2.18.19. and to this I made ſome good <hi>progreſs,</hi> and ſet my ſelf to the work in <hi>good earnest,</hi> and ſome years ſithence, <hi>abandoned</hi> the <hi>thoughts</hi> of any ſuch <hi>wickedneſs,</hi> and did <hi>reform</hi> ſome things that were amiſs, as to a more cloſe <hi>walking</hi> with <hi>God,</hi> in <hi>publike</hi> and <hi>private,</hi> in the <hi>Congregation</hi> and in my <hi>family,</hi> where I had been a little, yea too too much <hi>remiſs</hi> and <hi>careleſs,</hi> I <hi>laboured</hi> to make my <hi>peace within,</hi> for the <hi>terrors of the Lord had taken hold on me, Job</hi> 6.4. <hi>and had ſet themſelves in array against me, and the arrows of the Almighty ſtuck fast in me,</hi> the <hi>wrathful fire from above was within me, I could have no reſt, Pſalm</hi> 38.2.3.4. for <hi>when I ſaid I would forget my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, I would leave off my heavineſs, and comfort my ſelf, I knew that the Lord would not hold me innocent, and I was afraid of all my ſorrows, Job</hi> 9.27.28. <hi>compared with Exod.</hi> 34.7. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.5. <hi>for he would, I was ſure, viſit for all my ſins and iniquities, to the third and fourth generation of them that did hate him.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:166768:11"/>
            <p>The <hi>conſideration</hi> of this made me in <hi>ſecret weep bitterly,</hi> and I <hi>powred out my complaint to the Lord, John</hi> 242.2. I laid before him my <hi>trouble, my ſpirit was overwhelmed within me,</hi> I could not tell what to do, I was now to look death in the face; the <hi>Sword</hi> now might put an end to my <hi>daies;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Scotland</hi> July 1650.</note> 
               <hi>I looked on my right hand and beheld, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge failed me, and my hope was as the giving up the Ghoſt, Pſalm</hi> 142.4. <hi>compared with Joh.</hi> 11.20. <hi>and then I cried unto the Lord, I powred out my ſoul before him, I confeſſed my ſins in his ſight, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg I had done evil,</hi> and deſired he would <hi>purge me, and cleanſe me from mine iniquities throughly, and make me to hear joy and gladneſs;</hi> and that he would <hi>hide his face from my ſins, Pſalm</hi> 51.23.7.8.9. and deliver me, <hi>and not to take me away in his wrath, Pſalm</hi> 16.1. <hi>but to be merciful to me, and heal my ſoul, for I had ſinned againſt him,</hi> 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 30.20. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 41.5. <hi>and the Lord heard the voice of my ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, and gave me my hearts deſire; he delivered me and ſaved me, Pſalm</hi> 6.8. <hi>and healed the bones that were broken, and gave peace to the troubled ſpirit, Pſalm</hi> 30.2. and upon this it came into my heart what I ſhould now do for God, and that ſaying of that good man <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> came to my remembrance, <hi>Dan.</hi> 42. <hi>Wherefore O King let my counſel be acceptable unto thee, and break off thy ſins by righteouſneſs, and thy iniquities by ſhewing mercy to the poor, if it may be a length<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to thy tranquility:</hi> This Scripture did (I confeſs) much affect my heart, and I did <hi>vow</hi> to the <hi>Lord ſolemnly,</hi> I would lay out my ſelf for his glory, <hi>obey</hi> every <hi>truth,</hi> and <hi>break</hi> off every <hi>yoke:</hi> For the former, the <hi>ſeeking Gods glory,</hi> and <hi>obeying every truth</hi> in <hi>purſuance of my vow,</hi> I <hi>appeal</hi> to the <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>faithful brethren</hi> that are in that <hi>Troop</hi> that was not long ſithence mine, and to all the <hi>Congregations</hi> where I have been <hi>converſant,</hi> and in particular to the <hi>Congregation</hi> that now meeteth in Stone-chappel in <hi>Pauls London,</hi> where my moſt conſtant reſidency hath been.</p>
            <p>Yet for all this there were ſome of the <hi>Idols</hi> in the <hi>high places</hi> left ſtanding ſtill, 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 33.17. untaken away, which I ſhould have been as careful to have lain aſide, and have broken off from, as any elſe, and have known this to have been my duty, to have <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.31. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.8. had a <hi>grave, ſober,</hi> and an <hi>humble carriage</hi> in the <hi>things</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> that thereby I might have <hi>adorned the Goſpel of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt in all things, Tit.</hi> 2.10. and thus my <hi>ſpots</hi> continued, when I thought I had <hi>waſhed my ſelf clean, as with ſnow water, and had made my hands very clean, now the Lord</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Suffered me to fall thus, that I might make a clear and thorough work, and waſh and make all clean, to do away the ſmall ſpot as well as the great.</note> 
               <hi>he took me and threw me into the ditch, and my own cloaths they abhorred me, Job</hi> 9.30.31. and my ſpot hath not been the ſpot of his ſons or people; but of one that hath been perverſe, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.5. conſulting only with my own heart, which as the Prophets ſaith, Is <hi>deſperately wicked, and who can know it, Jer.</hi> 17.9. it being ſome years paſt: Thus was my ſoul decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and my <hi>heart</hi> did plead and hug me with peace; and like <hi>Lot,</hi> I
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:166768:11"/> thought in my ſelf that to deny it, being ſo long ſithence, it <hi>was but a little one, Gen.</hi> 19.20. but this now I have found, that on no one ſin goeth alone, but may well be called as that evil Spirit was which our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour caſt out of that man, who ſaid, being asked, his name was <hi>Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> becauſe <hi>many divels, Mark</hi> 5.9.15. <hi>Luke</hi> 8, 30. ſo I may ſay of this my <hi>ſin,</hi> it was <hi>Legion,</hi> that is, it was a <hi>ſin</hi> that brought many ſins with it; for after I had once denied it, then I was faſt bound and inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to ſtand to, and confirm my denial, that it was true.</p>
            <p>Now do but ſee how fooliſh and vain a thing it is, <hi>to forſake our own mercies, and to chuſe lying vanities, Jonah</hi> 2.8. <hi>to ſpeak wickedly for God, or to talk deceiptfully for him, Job</hi> 13.7. as if the truth of God, the glory and honor of his name, and wayes, <hi>ſtood in need of my lye, ſo to ſin that grace might abound,</hi> that good might come thereof, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.7.8. this now hath been my ſin, and this hath been my iniquity, in deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing truth, and ſpeaking falſly, not ſparing horrible wiſhes, bitter curſings and execrations on my ſelf, nor any means for the confirmation of what I had affirmed, (for which the Congregation did deal with me) though I did manifeſt by a large Declaration my ſorrow, true and hearty repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and that with tears; but the caſe was in their judgments difficult, (becauſe I had ſo greatly ſinned) whether my repentance was true or no; (which I ſay was) ſo that after a large debate, they were pleaſed by the greater number to declare me excluded; that truly I ſtand and <hi>tremble</hi> with the very <hi>thoughts of it,</hi> that <hi>God</hi> ſhould ſpare, and ſhould exerciſe any forbearance toward me, but might, and I <hi>admire</hi> at his <hi>grace,</hi> he did not ſtrike me <hi>dead,</hi> or ſhew ſome viſible <hi>judgment</hi> on me, to make me an <hi>example.</hi> But here is the <hi>great riches of his grace</hi> to be <hi>admired,</hi> that <hi>where ſin hath abounded</hi> (yea ſuperabounded) <hi>there grace hath much more abounded,</hi> Rom. 5.20, 21. that he did give me <hi>grace and time for repentance,</hi> yea hath alſo given <hi>repentance it ſelf,</hi> and <hi>bleſſed,</hi> and for ever <hi>bleſſed</hi> be his <hi>great name,</hi> though I muſt ſay with the Prophet, <hi>Lam</hi> 3.1. <hi>I am the man that have ſeen affliction, by the rod of his wrath, he hath builded againſt me, and compaſſed me with gall and gravell,</hi> Lam. 3.4. <hi>his loving kindneſſe that could not prevaile with me,</hi> to break off my iniquities, therefore his correcting hand, that hath taught me, though it hath been very ſore, yet I can ſay with the Prophet, <hi>Jeremiah</hi> 30.11. <hi>it hath been in meaſure, he hath not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes chid, neither hath he kept his anger, he hath not dealt with me after my ſins, neither rewarded me according to my iniquities,</hi> Pſal. 9.10. for he is and hath been to my ſoul <hi>exceeding plenteous in mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this (friends) ſin hath done to me, and brought upon me; 1. <hi>A ſtain and a blot,</hi> Prov. 6.33. and <hi>whither to cauſe my ſhame to go, I know not,</hi> 2 Sam. 13.13.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It hath cauſed my familiars and my friends, my <hi>companions with whom I have taken ſweet counſell together, and walked into the houſe of God in company, to reproach me,</hi> Pſal. 55.12.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:166768:12"/>3. <hi>It hath put my brethren far from me, and my acquaintance are verily eſtranged from me; my kinsfolk have failed, and my familiar friends have forgotten me,</hi> Job 19.13, 14.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It hath buried me in my <hi>good name, which is better then precious oyntment,</hi> Eccleſ. 7.1. <hi>and rather to be choſen then great riches,</hi> Pro. 22.1. what is it that it hath not brought upon me? all manner of miſchief, that as I have ſaid, ſin is the mother, yea the father alſo of all miſchief and evill, that I may truly ſay, that <hi>ſin is exceeding, or out of meaſure ſinfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I do teſtifie to all the world, that <hi>thorow grace,</hi> and of the <hi>rich love of God, Chriſt</hi> hath <hi>turned</hi> and caſt his <hi>gracious looks upon me,</hi> and darted his <hi>bleſſed rayes</hi> into my <hi>heart, as hath wrought unfained ſorrow</hi> and <hi>true repentance</hi> for my <hi>ſins never to be repented of,</hi> Lu. 22.61. <hi>for that ſorrow which is after a godly manner, worketh repentance to ſalvation not to be repented of,</hi> 2 Cor. 7.9, 10. and this I manifeſted to the <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>faithful Brethren</hi> of the <hi>Congregation meeting in Stone Chappell Pauls London with many teares:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Novemb. 6. 1653.</note> and I do by this crave <hi>pardon</hi> of all <hi>men</hi> that I have any wayes by <hi>lying lips</hi> in this matter <hi>abuſed,</hi> and do <hi>pray</hi> all the <hi>Saints</hi> and <hi>faithfull brethren</hi> of all the <hi>Congregations</hi> in the <hi>world,</hi> that I have any wayes <hi>offended, to forgive me, as God for Chriſts ſake hath forgiven them,</hi> Eph. 4.32.</p>
            <p>And now what ſhall I ſay, my <hi>grief</hi> is ſore, and my <hi>calamity</hi> great, <hi>I would it were by</hi> the godly wiſe throughly <hi>weighed, and that they were laid in the balance together, Iob</hi> 6.2. I am perſwaded they would ſay, that in this age there hath not appeared <hi>any ſorrow like my ſorrow, wherewith the Lord hath afflicted me in this his day of fierce anger, Lamen.</hi> 1.12. for it is to me ſo ſad and heavy, that truly I could wiſh, and <hi>oh that I might have my requeſt, that God would grant the thing that I long for, even that it would pleaſe God to deſtroy me, that he would let looſe his hand and cut me off, Iob</hi> 6.8.9. for I confeſs I am not worthy to be reckoned amongſt them that are living, but far better it would be for me to be where I ſhould be <hi>quiet, ſleep, and be at reſt, Iob</hi> 3.13. and be no longer ſuch a <hi>burthen to my ſelf, Iob</hi> 7.20. It is true I have ſinned againſt the Lord, who is <hi>the preſerver of men,</hi> and for that he hath made me to my <hi>neighbours a reproach, Pſalm</hi> 34.13. &amp; 74.4. yea it is ſo, as there was never any like it, that I, who not <hi>many moneths ſithence had the candle of the Lord ſhining on my head, and my ſteps were waſhed with butter, and the rock powred out rivers of oyl, Iob</hi> 29.23.6. that had my hands ſtrengthened to do the <hi>young men,</hi> yea the <hi>aged</hi> ſome right, and <hi>break the jaws</hi> of ſome wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men, and deliver ſome poor ſouls from their <hi>ſpoils,</hi> that was able in ſome ſmall meaſure to help the poor and needy, <hi>Iob</hi> 29.8.17. <hi>and ſend them away with a bleſſing;</hi> But now what is befallen me, ſhame and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt,<note n="†" place="margin">Mark it, and take heed of ſin, beware of ſin.</note> 
               <hi>and they that are younger then my ſelf, they have me in deriſion; I am their ſong and their by-word, Iob</hi> 30.1.9.10. <hi>they abhor me, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:166768:12"/> ſpare not to ſpit in my face;</hi> What is there, or can there be in this life a greater affliction then this, that my very enemies ſhould have their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire on me, that before ſtood in fear of me, ſhould now boaſt themſelves and triumph, this hath befallen <hi>the man</hi> that was ſo <hi>righteous;</hi> now the hand and <hi>judgment</hi> of <hi>God</hi> is againſt him for his actings againſt the <hi>King,</hi> and his <hi>Party;</hi> others they cry out, and rejoyce, and ſay, this is he that was ſo much againſt the <hi>Clergy,</hi> and they <hi>belch out</hi> their blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my now againſt the <hi>wayes</hi> of <hi>God, the young children they deſpiſe me, all my familiar friends and my old acquaintance are verily eſtranged from me, Job</hi> 19.13.14.18. they whom with all my heart I loved, are turned againſt me, though I have <hi>fill'd their bellies,</hi> and have <hi>cloathed their backs,</hi> have <hi>fed</hi> at my <hi>table,</hi> for whom I have been willing to ſpare no pains, but to lay out my ſelf to do them good, that <hi>they and theirs</hi> might receive <hi>refreſhment</hi> and <hi>comfort, theſe, O theſe!</hi> are turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, and <hi>reproach</hi> me <hi>bitterly,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">See what ſin doth bring to men.</note> ſo that my affliction is ſuch as it cannot be imagined, it is that cannot by any <hi>mortal</hi> be <hi>born, Pſalm</hi> 55.12. all indeed that have had <hi>any eſteem of me deſpiſe me, Lament.</hi> 1.8. <hi>becauſe I have ſinned grievouſly;</hi> and yet this is nothing, and not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, no not by ſome of my <hi>mothers children, for they are angry with me, and have put off all bowels of pity, Cant.</hi> 1.6. they have <hi>forſaken me as a brook, and as the ſtream of brooks they have paſſed away, Job</hi> 6.15. for they <hi>bind the yoke of my iniquities faſt on me with their hands till my ſtrength faileth me, and will not eaſe me, though it be but with the touch of one of their fingers, Mat.</hi> 23.4. <hi>Luk.</hi> 11.46. <hi>as if no pity were to be ſhown to him that is afflicted, Ioh</hi> 6.14. for in the <hi>houſe of my friends</hi> I have been <hi>wounded, Zech.</hi> 13.6. <hi>no love, patience; long-ſufferance,</hi> or <hi>forbearance,</hi> no <hi>brotherly kindneſs,</hi> or <hi>gentleneſs</hi> thought on,<note place="margin">I acknowledg it the just judgment of God againſt me, thus to puniſh me for my ſins by my deare friends, who truly I do think did it out of zeal to God, and deteſtation againſt my ſin, by which I had much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed them; yet I think there was ſome ſlip and weakneſs in their proceeding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, but I do heartily forgive them.</note> that ſo by <hi>meekneſs I might be taught and recovered out of the ſnare of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.25.29. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.12. ſo that I may ſay, where was the <hi>ſounding of bowels, where was mercy, it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained from me, Iſay</hi> 63.15. <hi>O Lord, I am oppreſſed, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake for me, Iſay</hi> 28.14. for thou haſt <hi>ſpoken once, yea twice,</hi> yet I <hi>perceived not, Iob</hi> 33.14. but, now thou haſt ſpoken <hi>terribly,</hi> and haſt <hi>broken</hi> all my <hi>bones;</hi> thou haſt <hi>cut</hi> me <hi>down</hi> like the <hi>graſs,</hi> thou haſt <hi>blown</hi> me <hi>away</hi> as <hi>chaff</hi> before the <hi>wind, Pſalm</hi> 1.4. ſo that I have known what and how fearful <hi>a thing it is to fall into the hand of God,</hi> and for him to enter into <hi>judgment with man, Heb.</hi> 10.30.31. yet he hath not <hi>retained his anger,</hi> nor conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued <hi>chiding,</hi> but hath <hi>in the midſt of wrath remembred mercy, Pſalm</hi> 103.8.9.10. <hi>Mica.</hi> 7.18. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.10. <hi>for with him is mercy and plenteous redemption;</hi> therefore let none <hi>rejoyce</hi> that I have <hi>fallen, I ſhall ariſe,</hi> yea the Lord hath raiſed me up, <hi>Mica.</hi> 7.8. and <hi>lifted up the light of his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:166768:13"/> upon me,</hi> having <hi>cheered</hi> the bones that were broken, and <hi>made me hear joy and gladneſs, Pſalm</hi> 4.6. &amp; 51.8. he having fulfilled his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, not to ſuffer me to be <hi>tempted above what I was able, but hath made a way to eſcape,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13. <hi>for the ſnare is broken, and my ſoul is eſcaped, my help is in the name of the Lord, Pſalm</hi> 124.6.7.</p>
            <p>And now <hi>what ſhall I render unto the Lord for all his benefits to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me, I will take the cup of ſalvation and call upon his name, I will pay my vows unto the Lord now in the preſence of all his people, Pſalm</hi> 116.12.13.14. <hi>and I and my houſe will ſerve the Lord, Nehe.</hi> 24.15. truly and ſincerely in <hi>righteouſneſs and true holineſs all the daies of my</hi> poor <hi>pilgrimage, Luk.</hi> 1.17. keeping <hi>under my body, and bringing it under ſubjection, mortifying all corruptions that are in my members that are upon the earth, Col.</hi> 35. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.27. laying aſide <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very weight, and thoſe ſins that do ſo eaſily beſet me, and run with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience the race that is ſet before me, Heb.</hi> 12.1. <hi>cleanſing my ſelf from all filthineſs of the fleſh, as well as ſpirit, perfecting holineſs in the fear of the Lord,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1. <hi>and this I will do</hi> (through his grace) <hi>for the Goſpel ſake,</hi> that if it be poſſible by all or any <hi>means, I may bring glory to God, and honor, and adorn the Goſpel of our Lord and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Jeſus Chriſt in all things, Tit.</hi> 2.10.</p>
            <p>And I will arm my ſelf to bear the <hi>reproaches of my mothers chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in the houſe of my friends, Cant.</hi> 1.6. compared with <hi>Zech.</hi> 13.7. and all the <hi>ſcoffings of the Michals and Iſmaels, Gen.</hi> 21.4. 1 <hi>Chro.</hi> 15.29. and if any <hi>Shemeis ſhall now curſe me,</hi> I will ſay, <hi>let him alone, for the Lord hath bidden him,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.11. and the Lord I know will <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite me good for their evil;</hi> and I will conclude with that ſaying, <hi>Mica.</hi> 7.9. <hi>I will bear the indignation of the Lord, becauſe I have ſinned againſt him.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:166768:13"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Excellency;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Confeſs my ſelf very much unworthy thus to trouble you, but a neceſſity lieth upon me, that I may now at laſt diſcharge a good conſcience, and be plain with God, my own heart, and your Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, that with the ſame mouth and lips by which I have lied and abuſed your ears, and with the ſame hand and pen acknowledg that I have dealt falſly and wickedly with your Excellency, and the reſt of your Officers, with whom I have had any thing to do about my buſineſs, eſpecially with thoſe Officers that were appointed by your Excellency to examine my buſineſs, I do hereby declare to my great ſhame, and acknowledg, that I did deal very falſly, hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically and wickedly, and all the means that poſſible my own baſe wicked heart could deviſe, I made uſe of, to cover and hide my ſins; I did not refrain from lies, vows, proteſtations, wiſhes, and execrations on my ſelf; alſo labouring by all the art I could to draw others into the ſame ſin with me, not ſparing the poor Church of God, amongſt whom I walked, to the great reproach and blaſphemy of the good name of God they profeſs; but the party whom it principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerned, I did frame words, and contrive mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, what ſhould be ſaid, and how the buſineſs ſhould go, ſo that truly I confeſs my ſin in that hath been very great; I do acknowledg, and I do bleſs God for his good grace to me, that after all my hardneſs and impenitency of heart, that he ſtirred up ſome of
<pb facs="tcp:166768:14"/> my brethren to deal with me, bringing me to a ſight of my great evils, and thereby alſo to great repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, for God hath ſpoken peace, and remembred mercy, for the which I do bleſs him, and ſhall all the daies of my life, love, honor and obey him, by a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, humble and righteous walking with him in the wayes of the Goſpel; and now I do humbly beg at your Excellencies hands, and all other your godly Officers hands pardon and forgiveneſs, as God for Chriſts ſake hath forgiven you: And my Lord, I have too too ſadly experienced your Excellencies words to me, or rather the Apoſtles, that God will not be mocked,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb</hi> 32.23. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.5.</note> but will make our ſins find us out; and truly I have found it true to purpoſe, though I knew it before, but ſin deceived me, the world had poſſeſſed my heart, the honor and profits of the ſame were ſnares to me, I pray God all may take warning by me, and not to love riches, honor, good name, more then the truth, and the honor of God, to beware that they be not deceived by their hearts, to think that God ſtands in need of our lies to honor and advantage his name, or wayes of his Goſpel, to ſin, that grace may abound.</p>
            <p>I do think it very meet to vindicate Col. <hi>Goffe,</hi> Col. <hi>Cooper,</hi> Lievt. Col. <hi>Maſon,</hi> Lievt. Col. <hi>Worſly,</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor <hi>Pecker,</hi> which were appointed by your Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to look into my cauſe, that they did faithfully and honeſtly, with a great deal of love and tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, endeavour to find out the truth, eſpecially Col. <hi>Goffe,</hi> and Lievt. Col. <hi>Maſon,</hi> that in my heart I did look on them as acting againſt me, as my very enemies, eſpecially Lievt. Col. <hi>Maſon</hi> was ſo buſie
<pb facs="tcp:166768:14"/> and reſtleſs, that truth might be found out; and for this I do pray Col. <hi>Goffe,</hi> and Lievt. Col. <hi>Maſon</hi> in particular forgiveneſs.</p>
            <p>And now my Lord, I cannot conclude without an acknowledgment of the many ſignal favours I have received from your Excellency, and how ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly your Excellency did deal with me about this buſineſs; ſo that I may ſay of your Excellency, as it is written of <hi>Joſeph, Mat.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>9. that your Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency being juſt, and full of pity, you were not mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to make me a publike example, but to put me off privily, caſting alſo in your thoughts how to do me good, that I might not be utterly ruined, all which I do with all humility and thankfulneſs acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, and am ſorry I have this ſad occaſion to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble your Excellency, and yet I rejoyce that God hath been pleaſed to be merciful to me: I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Not worthy to be reckoned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the living, much leſs your Excellencies poor unworthy ſervant; <hi>Edm. Chillenden.</hi>
               </signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Novemb.</hi> 30. 1653.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
